A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Lyle Saunders FA631
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Population Program, Office Files of Lyle Saunders
1963-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA631
2.4 Cubic Feet
The International Division/Population Papers of Lyle Saunders were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982. The papers consist of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. They are divided into two series: Population Files and Correspondence Files. Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Saunders' office.
Biographical / Historical
Lyle Saunders, Ford Foundation Program Officer in the International Division (ID), was a member of the Foundation staff from 1964 until 1975. During this period, he held the following positions:
• January 1975, Program Officer, Population Office and Asia and Pacific, ID • January 1974, Program Officer, Population Office, ID • January 1973, Advisor in Program Management seconded to the IBRD - National Family Planning Coordinating Board, Jakarta, ID • January 1971, Program Advisor, A&P, Southeast Asia (Thailand), ID • May 1968, Program Officer, Population Office, ID • July 1967, Program Advisor, Population Office (Malaysia), ID • January 1967, Program Officer, Population Office, ID • October 1966, Associate Director, Population Program, OD • February 1964, Program Associate, Population Program, OD
Lyle Saunders was born October 16, 1907. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees in 1938 and 1943 respectively, from the University of New Mexico. He did additional course work at the Universities of Chicago and Texas.
Prior to Saunders' career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
• 1942-1951, University of New Mexico Assistant Professor of Sociology, School of Inter-American Affairs • 1951-1964, University of Colorado, Associate Professor of Sociology, Associate Professor of the Department of Preventive Medicine, Acting Head of the Department of Preventive Medicine and Public Health, School of Medicine, Director of the Institute of Behaviorial Science • 1961-1962, Government of India Advisor in Research and Evaluation, Central Health Education Bureau
Following his reitrement from the Ford Foundation, Mr. Saunders served the Foundation as a consultant on population related matters off and on from March 1976 until September 1980. He now resides in Santa Fe, New Mexico.
Scope and Contents
These papers, which consist of two boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports, are concerned with the International Division's Population Program for the years 1963 to 1970.
The papers, which are broad in scope, yet lacking in quantity and depth, include material related to population conferences attended by FF staff, overseas program population files, budget material, and other areas of Foundation family planning involvement, including contraceptive research. The papers are indicative of the role Saunders played within the Population Program.
There is also one box of correspondence that Saunders maintained with FF colleagues, grantee organizations, and other individuals in the population field.
Arrangement
The International Division/Population Papers of Lyle Saunders are divided into two series:
I. Population Files
II. Correspondence Files
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned material. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Population Files, 1963-1970; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Population Files (1963-1970), is the most substanitve. It contains material on the activities of the International Division's Population Program.
  Arrangement
  The files, which maintain the order established by Saunders' office, fall into five categories: Conference Files, which are arranged in reverse chronological order; Overseas Program Interest Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order; Family Planning and Population Program Budget Files, which are both arranged in reverse chronological order; and Grant Proposal Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Political Science in Population Studies, Carolina Population Center Workshop, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C. December 10-11, 1970, 1970 December - November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Southeast Asia Ministers' Conference, Kuala Lumpur, October 1970, 1970 November - July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Population Communication Conference, Tehran, June 6-18, 1970, 1970 April - 1969 November (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Second National Seminar on General Consequences of Population Growth, Malaysia, March 1970, 1970 March - 1969 August (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Society for Internatioanl Development, New Delhi, Nov. 14-17, 1969, 1969 August - July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Villa Serbelloni Conference on Population, October 20-22, 1969, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Indian Population Advisors Meeting, Altamont, Milbrook, New York, Sep. 23-24, 1969, 1969 September - February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IPPF Meeting at the Ford Foundation, September 22, 1969, 1969 September - July (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Research Planning Conference, Budapest, September 18-19, 1969, 1969 December - August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Workshop on Contraceptive Specifications, August 11-12, 1969, 1969 August - July (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interregional Workshop on Programmes of Training in the Field of Population, Elsinore, Denmark, June 19-30, 1967, 1967 June - March (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NICHD Conference on Behavioral Sciences and Family Planning, Bethesda, Maryland, June 7-9, 1967, 1967 June - March (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ROCAP Conference, San Jose, Costa Rica, February 6-8, 1967, 1967 April - 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Macy Foundation Conference, NY,NY, January 6, 1967, 1967 February - January (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notre Dame Conference on Population, South Bend, Indiana, Dec. 1-3, 1966, 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conference on the Physiology of Human Reproduction, Venice, May, 1966, 1966 May - 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Overseas Program Interest, Latin America - General, 1967 June - 1966 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Brazil, 1967 March - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Chile, 1967 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Colombia, 1967 May - 1964 August (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Costa Rica, 1967 June - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Dominican Republic, 1967 March - January (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Overseas Program Interest - El Salvador, 1967 May - 1966 October (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Guatemala, 1967 March (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Mexico, 1967 June - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Peru, 1967 April - January (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Overseas Program Interest - S&SE Asia - Malaysia, 1968 June - 1965 January (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Overseas Program Interest - Indonesia, 1967 June - May (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - S&SE Asia/India/Social/Sciences, 1968 May - April (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Family Planning - World Activities, 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Family Planning - USA, 1966 July (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Contraceptives, 1968 September - May (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Population Program Budget Material, 1967 June - 1965 April (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Population Program - Fellowships Available, 1965 November (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Population Program - Staff Discussions, 1967 April - 1966 November (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Population Program - Staff Discussions, 1966 November - 1963 November (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Grant Proposals: BEMFAM, 1967 March - 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Grant Proposals: Baltimore Planned Parenthood, 1967 January; 1966 October (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grant Proposals: Pan American Federation of Associations of Medical Schools, 1967 June - March (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Grant Proposals: University of Rio de Janeiro, 1967 March - 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grant Proposals: Urban League, 1967 May (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Correspondence Files, 1964-1970; II
  Series II, Correspondence Files (1964-1970), contains correspondence generated by Mr. Saunders during his years at the Foundation.
  The correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - AM - AN, 1964 May - 1966 February (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - BE - BR, 1964 April - 1966 April (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - CA - CR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - DA - DE, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - ER, 1964 June; 1966 June (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - FE - FR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Freedman, Ronald, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - GA - GR, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - HA - HO, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - IN - IR, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - India - Freyman, Nyswander, Dhillon, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - JA - JO, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - KA - KO, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - LE - LO, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - MA - MU, 1964-1965; 1966 May (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mc, 1964 December (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - NI - NY, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Nurses Manual, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - OG - OU, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - PA - PI, 1964; 1965 August (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - QU, 1965 April (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - RA - RU, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - SA - SU, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Samora, Julian, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Sweeney, W.O., 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - TA - TI, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - VI, 1965 February (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - WA - WO, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - ZE, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Appendix A: Lyle Saunders Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished Ford Foundation reports by Lyle Saunders were removed from the papers. They are listed in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Colombia Log, 1964 September 2-19 (Report 10064)
  - Colombia Log, 1964 November 2-21 (Report 10065)
  - Colombia Log, 1965 October 9-15 (Report 10066)
  - Colombia Notes, 1966 April 18-24 (Report 10067)
  - Draft - [Educational Institutions], n.d. (Report 10,068 Draft)
  - Elements of Population Strategy, 1970 August (Report 7610)
  - Family Planning Research and Evaluation: Needs for the Future, 1965 August (Report 10069)
  - Family Planning: The World-Wide View, 1966 December (Report 486)
  - An Idea for Stimulating New Acceptances and Distributing Information About Places and Times of Family Planning Clinic Service, 1967 October 12 (Report 10070)
  - Ideas and Suggestions for an Asian Population Organization. August 28, 1970., 1970 August 28 (Report 10071)
  - IPPF Interest in Bemfam Training Progress, 1966 December 27 (Report 10072)
  - La Ceja Seminar, 10/13/65, LS Comments at Closing Session, 1965 October 13 (Report 10073)
  - Log Notes - Cairo, 1967 February (Report 10074)
  - Macy Foundation Conference on International Health Programs, 1967 January 6 (Report 10075)
  - Malaysia and Singapore (Report 10076)
  - Malaysia National Family Planning Board, 1970 March 27 (Report 10077)
  - National Family Planning Board - Maylasia - Suggestions for an Information Programme, 1967 August 3 (Report 10078)
  - National Family Planning Programs: Organization and Administration - Discussion Paper, 1968 February (Report 10079)
  - Notes on Fifth Notre Dame Conference on Population, December 1-3, 1966, 1966 December (Report 10080)
  - The Organization of a National Family Planning Program: Some Preliminary Considerations, 1965 January (Report 2884)
  - Political Science in Population Studies - Action Policy Needs, 1970 December (Report 7621)
  - Population - Central America, 1966 November 10 (Report 6957)
  - Population - Colombia Third Seminar on Demography, Buga, Valle, April 20-23, 1966, 1966 May 12 (Report 10081)
  - Population, Development and Welfare in Malaya, 1964 June (Report 4088)
  - Population - Dominican Republic, 1967 February 1 (Report 10082)
  - Population Policy: Beyond Family Planning, 1970 February (Report 4032)
  - [Population Study in Central America - Observations], 1966 (Report 10086)
  - Research and Evaluation: Needs for the Future, 1965 August (Report 461)
  - Recent Fertility Trends in West Malaysia (Report 10087)
  - Resistances and Misconceptions About Family Planning, 1968 February (Report 10089)
  - Some Simple-Minded Notes on Population Strategy, 1970 June 6 (Report 10083)
  - Some Thoughts About Next Steps in the National Family Planning Program of the United Arab Republic, 1965 November 12 (Report 10084)
  - A Suggested Procedure for a Population Program for Malaya, 1965 February 19 (Report 459)
  - Suggestions for an International Population Research Institute (IPRI), 1970 July 22 (Report 4900)
  - [Where we Are], 1968 August 6 (Report 10085)
  - Workshop on Contraceptive Specifications, 1969 August 13 (Report 10088)
- Appendix B: Other FF Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished reports written by other FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers. They are listed alphabetically by author. For each author, the reports are arranged in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Almeida, Ivan. Requested Funding of Reproductive Biology Research at the Department of Obstetric and Gynecology, Faculty of Medicine, Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, 1967 March 23 (Report 10046)
  - Alvarez, Jose. BEMFAM Project Proposal, 1967 March 10 (Report 10047)
  - Evaluation of Grant Request from IPPF, 1968 August 8 (Report 10048)
  - Bell, David. The "International Division" - General Shape and Content, 1966 October 19 (Report 9040)
  - Bresnan, Jack. The Social Sciences in India: A Preliminary View, 1968 April 25 (Report 3502)
  - Ensminger, Douglas. Family Planning - Meeting with Mr. K.K. Shah Minister, Health, Family Planning, Works, Housing and Urban Development (Report 10049)
  - Ford Foundation. Communications for Information and Motivation in Family Planning, 1966 September (Report 6948)
  - Ford Foundation. Conference on the Physiology of Human Reproduction Sponsored by the Ford Foundation Population Program, 1966 May (Report 10050)
  - Ford Foundation. Ford Foundation Programs in Population, 1966 June (Report 10051)
  - Ford Foundation. International Division Meeting, Beirut, January 9-11, 1967, 1967 January 31 (Report 8901)
  - Ford Foundation. International Division - Population - Budget for Fiscal 1968-72, 1967 April (Report 10052)
  - Ford Foundation. International Division - Program Budget Request, Fiscal Year 1968 (Report 10053)
  - Ford Foundation. The Nirodh Marketing Programme - The Case For a New Organisational Base, 1969 June (Report 3677)
  - Ford Foundation. Population Office - "Rough-Cut" Budget for Fiscal 1968-72, 1967 February (Report 10054)
  - Freedman, Ronald. Comments on Evaluation of the West Bengal Family Planning Program, 1969 June 9 (Report 1494)
  - Hardee, J. Gilbert. Report on the Southeast Asian Ministerial Conference on Family and Population Planning, 1970 October 28 (Report 10055)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Population - Program Planning Budget 1966- 1967-1968, 1965 April 19 (Report 10056)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Population - Program Planning Budget 1967- 1968-1969, 1966 April 1 (Report 10057)
  - Harkavy, Oscar. Relations With Population Council, 1967 February 3 (Report 10058)
  - Hjort, Howard. A Programme Evaluation System for the Family Planning Program of the Government of India, 1969 May 29 (Report 1493)
  - Howe, Harold. Interdisciplinary Research and Teaching at Universities Related to India's Population Problems, 1969 August 12 (Report 4106)
  - McDaniel, Joseph. Actions Approved by the Board of Trustees on September 28-29, 1966, 1966 October 11 (Report 10059)
  - Merrill, Malcolm. Report of Ford Foundation Consultation Visit to India Nov. 16 - Dec. 4, 1963 (Report 391)
  - Radel, David, and Perkin, Gordon. Current Status of Family Planning Programs in the United States, 1966 October (Report 454)
  - Radel, David. Possible Social Science Research Contributions to Family Planning: Discussion Paper, 1956 November 22 (Report 4895)
  - Radel, David. A Selected List of Fellowships for Training in the United States in Demography, Family Planning, and Reproductive Biology, 1965 November (Report 10060)
  - Reynolds, Richard. Some Observations on the Indian Family Planning Program, 1969 April (Report 7634)
  - Simmons, Ozzie. IPPF - Related Activities in Chile, 1969 April 11 (Report 10062)
  - Simpson, S.J.R. Consulting Report: Family Planning Communications in Nigeria, 1969 March (Report 2332)
  - Staples, Eugene. Assignment of Dr. Anna Southam and Mr. Lyle Saunders as Program Advisors on Population Questions in Asia, 1968 May 6 (Report 10061)
  - Sweeney, William O. Central America and Some Caribbean Countries: A Report on Population and Family Planning Information, Education and Communications Programs. And Problems, 1970 July (Report 2333)
  - Sweeney, William O. El Salvador: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning, 1970 February (Report 2334)
  - Sweeney, William O. Guatemala: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education Programs in Family Planning, 1970 June (Report 3808)
  - Sweeney, William O. Jamaica: A Survey of Communications, Information and Education in Family Planning, 1970 November (Report 2331)
  - Sweeney, William O. Kenya: Developing a Family Planning Communications Plan for 1970-1971, 1970 January (Report 9384)
  - Sweeney, William O. Suggestions for an Education and Public Information Program for Nutrition, Maternal and Child Health, and Population, in Costa Rica, 1969 September (Report 2335)
  - Sweeney, William O. Summary of Activities in El Salvador - Week of February 8 through 14th, 1970 February 14 (Report 10063)